American Montessori Society Records 2006.0230
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
American Montessori Society Records
undated, 1907-2012
2006.0230
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
51.0 Linear feet
The American Montessori Society (AMS) Records document the history of an important American educational organization, and consist of printed, typescript, and handwritten materials; sound recordings; films; photographs; and slides. The collection, although not complete, reflects AMS's professional and administrative activities and also provides historical information about the Montessori system of education in general.
American Montessori Society.
History
Maria Montessori ( 1870-1952 ), the first woman in Italy to receive a medical degree from the University of Rome, developed her theories of education at the turn of the century while working as a young doctor in an asylum for mentally disabled children. In the Montessori method, children use special learning materials in a prepared environment to sequentially develop and master concepts and motor skills. Teachers guide but do not control, each child progresses at his or her own pace, and the noncompetitive atmosphere of the classroom allows working for the pleasure of learning rather than from fear of punishment or anticipation of rewards.
Dr. Montessori developed an international following, and in 1913 and 1915 she toured the United States, lecturing on her educational theories to enthusiastic acclaim. Yet by the 1920s her ideas had been rejected by mainstream American educators. This effectively killed the Montessori movement in the United States for the next several decades, although it continued to flourish in Europe, especially among Catholic educational institutions.
In the late 1950s Nancy McCormick Rambusch, a young teacher who had undergone Montessori training in London, became inspired with the idea of reviving Montessori education in America. Initially conducting classes from her New York apartment, she soon founded and became headmistress of Whitby, a lay-Catholic school in Greenwich, Connecticut, which became the flagship school of the American Montessori revival. Rambusch and Whitby gained a reputation and supporters; they and the Montessori method soon became the subjects of articles and interviews in both Catholic and secular journals and magazines. They also attracted the attention of the Association Montessori Internationale ( AMI), the guardian and promulgator of Maria Montessori's ideals under the directorship of her son, Mario, who authorized Rambusch to act as AMI's representative in America. This led, in 1960, to the founding of the American Montessori Society ( AMS), with Rambusch as its first president.
During the early years the fortunes of AMS and Whitby School were intertwined; the two institutions even shared Board members. Although Rambusch was active in Catholic circles, she recognized that Montessori had to transcend religious boundaries and would have to acquire nonsectarian appeal if it was to succeed in the United States. She also firmly believed that aspects of the Montessori method had to be modified to accommodate the culture of mid-twentieth- century America and its children, and that the movement should not be confined to private institutions.
These ideas strained relations with AMI, which felt that Dr. Montessori's principles were universal and could not be modified without destroying their integrity. Despite good-faith attempts on both sides, the philosophical differences could not be reconciled, while additional controversies over finances and control deepened the rift. Ultimately, in 1963, AMI withdrew its recognition of AMS as a Montessori society, and from that point until the present AMS has existed independently of AMI.
Nineteen-sixty-three was a critical year for AMS. Nancy McCormick Rambusch had been travelling around the country tirelessly promoting Montessori and drumming up support among educators and parents. The results were overwhelmingly positive: the number of Montessori schools in America increased and the AMS office in Greenwich was flooded with requests for information about the method and about how to open Montessori schools. The society was weakened, however, by conflicts not only with AMI but within AMS itself. Moreover, the administrative affairs of the office were in chaos, and the organization was in danger of disintegrating.
This situation was remedied when Cleo Monson was hired in January 1963 as Executive Secretary to reorganize AMS's office, but her administrative abilities soon rendered her indispensable as the coordinator of virtually all the society's activities. In 1973 she became the first National Director, a position of pivotal importance that she essentially created and that she held until her retirement in 1978. In her own way she was as responsible as Nancy McCormick Rambusch for the existence of AMS.
In 1963, six months after Monson arrived, Rambusch resigned as president and embarked upon a distinguished career in children's education that continued until her death in 1994. Also in 1963, the national office of AMS moved from Greenwich to New York, where it has since remained.
Following the turbulence of these early years, AMS found firmer footing and began to flourish. As the society grew, it had to cope with the practical issues that face all organizations, including fundraising, formation of policies, codification of professional standards and ethics, and public relations, both within and without the Montessori community. Various committees and programs sprang into existence to meet these needs, and this required the talents and resources of members willing to organize and direct these important activities. Within a decade of its existence, therefore, AMS's internal structure necessarily increased in complexity. Yet the society continued to avoid bureaucracy as much as possible by using the main office in New York as a coordinating hub.
Because Montessori schools were not required to affiliate with the national organization, AMS sought to establish relationships with local schools through various forms of outreach. It published literature about the Montessori method and AMS, collected research, some of which appeared in the society's various journals and newsletters, and established the Consultation Program, in which trained consultants would visit affiliated schools, observe classes and the physical environment, and offer suggestions and feedback. AMS developed standards for teacher training and certification as well as pedagogical resources to meet Montessori educational needs.
AMS's seminars and conferences also served to foster communication, professional growth, and a shared sense of identity among Montessori teachers. A national seminar was held annually, and several regional conferences took place each year. These meetings featured lectures, workshops, presentations, and exhibits, and allowed members to network, exchange ideas, and develop or hone their teaching skills. Portions of these seminars were recorded or filmed to serve as future resources. The society was very proud of the success of its first International Symposium, held in Athens in 1979, which featured as speakers several internationally renowned educators and scholars.
Throughout the 1970s and 1980s, AMS constantly sought to widen its appeal. Its ties with the Comite Hispano Montessori, for instance, enabled the Montessori method and resources to thrive in Spanish-speaking communities in the Americas and the Caribbean. AMS collected literature from and established relationships with other educational groups and organizations, including the National Association for the Education of Young Children and the Child Development Associate Consortium, and concerned itself with home schooling, day care, and alternative educational methods such as the Waldorf Institutes. In this way it attempted to keep abreast of contemporary developments in children's education and resist parochialism by entering into dialogue with those who shared AMS's concerns for the educational welfare of children.
AMS succeeded in reviving the Montessori method in the United States and gaining recognition for it as a valid educational system. The society has become the foremost resource in America for Montessori education and teacher training. Through its varied activities it continues to provide information, support, and advice to schools, teachers, and parents, and to integrate the ideas of Maria Montessori and her many followers into the structure of American education.
Scope and Content
The documents in the American Montessori Society ( AMS) Records extend from the mid-1950s through the mid-1990s, though the bulk falls between 1960 and 1985. They encompass a variety of subjects and activities, including routine administrative and financial records, research, historical correspondence and writings, official publications, and publicity.
The early history of AMS appears in Series VI, VII, and VIII, which include Board of Directors' minutes, financial reports, articles on the Montessori movement and AMS, and correspondence among key figures in the movement and organization. These papers chronicle the founding of AMS in connection with Whitby School in Greenwich, Connecticut; the difficult relationship between AMS and the Association Montessori Internationale ( AMI); and the problems AMS had to confront as it established its reputation and authority as a promoter of Montessori education. Especially important in this regard are the files of Nancy McCormick Rambusch (Series VII), the founder of AMS; this series provides historical information not only about AMS but also about the personal and professional life of Rambusch as revealed in correspondence, research, articles, and interviews.
AMS's minutes and bylaws may be found in Series I and II, respectively. Series II though is incomplete. Minutes are also included in the records found in Series IV and VI. The Administrative Files (Series III) deal with professional and operational administrative aspects of AMS and some of its committees and progr AMS. They include, among other documents, a policy statement (1963), correspondence of the Educational Advisory Committee, fundraising appeals and brochures, drafts of the AMS Management Guide, and correspondence and legal information about evaluating the credentials of foreign Montessori teacher trainees. There are also leases and maintenance correspondence for the AMS offices in New York, and personnel correspondence about insurance progr AMS for Montessori teachers.
The Mailings Scrapbooks in Series IV contain the letters, publicity, publications, and other literature generated by AMS and sent to its members and Board members during 1974-1983, affording a general overview of the society's functions and activities for that period. Series XV also contains scrapbooks of AMS's public-relations efforts as it sought to advertise its mission, and includes lists of AMS publications and materials. AMS also sought outreach through films, and the correspondence, scripts, and publicity for several film projects will be found in Series XVI.
Historical background and information on the Montessori movement and its founder will be found in Series X. Writings by and about Maria Montessori, transcripts of her historic lectures given in California in 1915, and articles about the history and evolution of the method both in general and in the United States are included; many of these papers were donated to the society by Montessori educators and supporters.
As the movement gained momentum, Montessori educators and scholars conducted and published research on a variety of relevant educational topics. The AMS office collected various papers, articles, bibliographies, and abstracts to serve as an in-house resource for Montessori scholarship, and these will be found in Series XI. Although they date largely from the 1960s and thus do not reflect the most current research, they provide a glimpse of the state of American Montessori studies at the time. Series IX contains pedagogical resources that show how Montessori education was actually conducted in the classroom, including lesson plans, outlines, and the Teacher's Manual for the 1966-1976 Teacher Training Program.
AMS published numerous journals, newsletters, and other publications, and many of these appear in Series XIV. All the titles represented contain significant gaps but still permit the reader to grasp the scope of the organization's activities and interests through the years. Non- AMS publications will be found in Series XXI, and include writings on Montessorian topics by organizations other than AMS, including AMI. Of particular interest is Mario Montessori's "yellow paper," which set forth AMI's philosophical disagreements with AMS in the early 1960s.
AMS encouraged affiliation by Montessori schools, and this topic is covered in Series XVII, which contains lists of affiliates, bylaws and administrative forms of individual schools, statistical data, and various brochures and other information regarding affiliated schools in general and also specific schools. One of the ways AMS sought to cement ties between affiliates and the national society was through the Consultation Program, the records of which are located in Series XII. They include general correspondence as well as files of individual consultants and several coordinators of the Program, and offer insights into the operations of this important group. The activities of the Comite Hispano Montessori, an association for Spanish-speaking Montessorians in North, Central, and South America as well as the Caribbean, are reflected in the correspondence, publicity, directories, and consultation reports that comprise Series XIX.
In Series XIII are located files for various national and regional seminars from 1963-1990. Registration lists, correspondence dealing with exhibitors and presenters, brochures and programs, financial reports and records, and evaluation questionnaires allow an understanding of the importance of these meetings as vehicles for fostering, maintaining, and developing aspects of the Montessori method.
AMS also interacted with organizations and concerns not directly within the Montessori orbit. Series V chronicles the relationship between AMS and government agencies, especially the Pennsylvania Department of Education, as the society sought to achieve official recognition of Montessori teacher-training methods and educational instruction. AMS's connections with other groups relevant to its interests are depicted in Series XX, which includes articles, brochures, and correspondence. Represented are day-care and home-schooling organizations, educational toy companies, and Waldorf Institutes. Series 18 is devoted to the Child Development Associate Consortium ( CDAC), of which AMS eventually became a member.
Audiocassettes, audiotapes, CDs and phonograph records are located in Series XXII. The tapes and cassettes contain lectures, speeches, and workshops conducted mainly at various AMS seminars from the 1960s through the 1980s. Films and videocassettes about various aspects of the Montessori method are located in Series XXIII. Of interest is an interview with Nancy McCormick Rambusch and Cleo Monson about the beginnings of AMS, taped in 1986.
Photographs and slides are included in Series XXIV. The slides illustrate Montessori teaching activities and events, such as the Montessori Centennial Celebration in 1970. The photographs cover a wide range of professional and social activities, including seminars. Depicted are many of the individuals, including Nancy McCormick Rambusch, who are represented in the papers of the collection.
Arrangement
Series I: Minutes ( 1963-1995 ) include the minutes from Board of Directors' meetings, including various emendations, arranged chronologically. See also Series IV and VI.
Series II: By-Laws and Amendments ( undated, circa 1960-1973 ) contain the By-Laws of AMS with changes and corrections over the years, arranged chronologically. Not all years within the range are included.
Series III: Administrative Files ( undated, 1959-1978 ) includes various files dealing with administrative aspects of AMS and its various committees regarding professional activities and day-to-day operations. Subseries A contains AMS's Policy Statement from 1963 and the National Director's Report to the Board of Directors from 1976. Subseries B contains various versions of the AMS Management Guide, a manual on setting up Montessori schools, featuring included or discarded items such as sample policies and forms for admissions and scholarships, many from Montessori-affiliated schools, and procedures on teaching methods. Subseries C contains correspondence, mainly from 1963-1964, of the Educational Advisory Committee. Subseries D deals with the problem of evaluating the academic credentials of foreign Montessori teaching trainees. The materials, which include pamphlets and correspondence, date mainly from 1965-1974; much of the correspondence is with the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (see also Series V). Subseries E consists of correspondence (1959-1978) about the Visitor Exchange Program and includes legal information from the Department of State and the Federal Register. Subseries F contains the proceedings of a 1973 seminar designed to share details about models of day care and about needs and goals that helped shape Montessori programs. Subseries G contains correspondence, appeals, brochures, and response cards pertaining to the 1981 drive to raise funds for AMS among affiliated schools. Subseries H includes office-maintenance and personnel-related records, including leases (1963-1973, with gaps) for the AMS offices at 175 Fifth Avenue, correspondence about building maintenance, and correspondence regarding insurance benefits and plans for Montessori teachers.
Series IV: Mailing Scrapbooks ( 1974-1983 ) contains ten scrapbooks, compiled annually, bring together a collection of items mailed to AMS members and Board members each year. They feature such documents as Board minutes, reports on the Consultation Program, financial reports, publications such as AMS News, questionnaires, information on conferences and seminars, and brochures and publicity. Many of these items may be duplicated in other series.
Series V: Federal and State Agencies ( 1962-1983 ) conatins correspondence primarily with the Pennsylvania Department of Education, including the State Board of Private Academic Schools, and details the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania's recognition and licensing of Montessori teacher-training methods and the recognition of the Montessori method as a valid form of instruction in private licensed schools. Included are various state criteria for licensing, such as the Rules and Regulations Governing Private Academic Schools and Agents (1980). The policy changes by the State Board of Private Academic Schools toward Montessori schools is also documented. Some correspondence with the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare is also included (see also Series III, Subseries D).
Series VI: Royall O'Brien Files ( 1962 ) includes materials, originally in a looseleaf binder, of Royall O'Brien, an AMS Board member from 1962-1968. They document the early history of AMS in 1962, and include minutes, correspondence, administrative and financial reports, memoranda, and other records that O'Brien would have received as a Board member. Many are duplicated elsewhere, especially in Series VII. The original arrangement of the papers has been retained.
Series VII: Nancy McCormick Rambusch Files ( undated, circa 1956-1994 ) chronicles a portion of the professional life and activities of Nancy McCormick Rambusch, the founder of AMS and the person most responsible for reviving the Montessori movement in the United States. Subseries A, arranged chronologically from the late 1950s-1977 (with the bulk 1960-1963) contains general and business correspondence relating to Rambusch's activities at Whitby School and the early years of AMS. Included are minutes from the Boards of both Whitby and the AMS, Rambusch's resignations as president of AMS and as headmistress of Whitby, and letters from individuals interested in the Montessori method or wishing to open Montessori schools. Telegrams and letters to and from Mario Montessori, Rambusch, and others in AMI and AMS chart the gradually deteriorating relationship between the two groups (see also Series VIII). Especially significant in this regard are two documents of Mario Montessori: the 1959 paper in which he appoints Rambusch as an official representative of AMI in the United States and authorizes a mandate to begin an American Montessori group, and a typescript version of the "yellow paper" written several years later, in which he outlines his philosophical disagreements with AMS that eventually led to a rift between the organizations (see Series XXI for the printed version). Some of the documents are fragile thermofaxes. There are numerous handwritten letters, usually by Rambusch's friends, that are personal but deal largely with Montessori matters. Most of the correspondence is to Rambusch, with relatively little from her; some letters are about her and are included here because they deal with topics relevant to the subseries. There are also letters and memos on administrative matters that would have concerned her as president of AMS. Subseries B consists largely of handwritten letters, postcards, and notes from friends on personal, social, and family matters, though some mention Montessori in passing. Many are by friends and teachers from Rambusch's student years, and depict the Catholic social and educational circles in which she moved and through which the Montessori movement gained a foothold in the United States. Some of the correspondence is undated; most falls between 1961 and 1963. Subseries C contains research and articles by Rambusch and writings about her. Included are typescripts of articles and papers, arranged alphabetically by title and dating from the 1960s through the 1980s, that she wrote on various aspects of children's education and the Montessori system (additional materials by Rambusch will be found in Series IX). In addition to manuscripts (both typed and handwritten) of lectures, speeches, and interviews that she gave, there is also an annotated bibliography and critique of selected works on Montessori compiled by Rambusch in 1962 (see Series XI, Subseries B for other bibliographies on Montessori research). This subseries also contains articles about Rambusch that appeared in various newspapers and magazines, many of them Catholic. Most date from the early 1960s and many profile Whitby School in connection with the Montessori method and AMS. Included are reviews of Rambusch's book, Learning How To Learn, published in 1962. Some of the newspaper clippings are brittle. Subseries D contains announcements of Rambusch's illness and death in 1994, and includes correspondence regarding her funeral, professional tributes, the program from her funeral Mass, and discussions about the establishment by AMS of the Dr. Nancy McCormick Rambusch Lecture Series and The Founder's Endowment Fund in her memory. There is also a folder of obituary clippings, some of them brittle.